So there is different types of coats on long coated breeds.
You can have a harsh course coat and you can also have a dog or a dog breed that has a finer softer silkier coat.
The individual dogs are the breeds that have a finer softer long coat are going to require a lot more maintenance.
It is going to be more difficult to keep them brushed out because that fine coat is going to mat a little bit more.
An individual dog or a breed with a harsher courser coat is going to be a little bit easier to manage, easier to keep brushed out.
Again with any breeds that are supposed to have one coat type, you might have individuals or groups of individuals with another coat type.
It is much easier to maintain a harsh coated long haired dog than a finer coated dog and so if that is within your breed standard, you want to make sure that, that dog the dog that you get has that kind of harsh coat.
You can tell the individual hairs are thicker, you can tell by rasping the hair between your fingers and you can tell just by touching the overall coat and looking at the adults and seeing how easy it is to brush through the adults.
The difference between a course harsh coat and a soft fine coat and for breeds with a soft finer coat is appropriate, that's fine to get individuals of that coat type.
You just want to make sure that the grooming requirements are not going to be over what they would be for a normal dog within that breed standard.